DC Oral History Collaborative Collection 180
People's Archive, MLK Library
- Series 7: Asian American Voices in the Making of Washington, D.C.'s Cultural Landscape Oral History Project, 2017-2018
  - Sub-Series 1: Interviews
    - Bobby Pradachith interview, 2018-05-29; dcpl_dcohc007_04.wav
      Written permission from the narrator is required to access this collection.
      Bobby Pradachith was born in Alexandria, Virginia in 1993 to Lao immigrant parents. As a child he was exposed to Lao cuisines through family gatherings, his mother's catering business, and the family restaurant Padaek. While attending the culinary arts program at Annandale High School in Annandale, Virginia, Pradachith became interested in pursuing a career as a professional chef. He attended Culinary Institute of America in New York, New York and completed externships in restaurants with Asian American chefs. He worked at Washington, D.C. restaurants Toki Underground and barmini before partnering with his mother Seng Luangrath to open Thip Khao in Columbia Heights. Pradachith is active in the Washington, D.C. chef community and uses food to tell the story of his family's Lao heritage.
      Bobby Pradachith discusses growing up the child of immigrants with influences of Lao culture, food, and language, attending the culinary arts program at Annandale High School, attending the Culinary Institute of America in New York, New York, externing with Asian American chefs, working at his family's restaurants, and building relationships with chefs in Washington, D.C. Pradachith also discusses his strong relationship with his family and learning of his parents' difficult departure from Laos.
    - Danny Lee interview, 2018-08-20; dcpl_dcohc007_01.wav
      Danny Lee was born in Washington, D.C. in 1981 to Korean immigrant parents. He grew up in Falls Church and Vienna, Virginia and attended Thomas Jefferson High School for Science and Technology in Alexandria, Virginia. While Lee was in high school his father passed away, which led his mother to open an American Chinese franchise restaurant in Reagan National Airport to support the family. After graduating from the University of Virginia in Charlottesville, Virginia, Lee worked as a paralegal and then an office manager/event coordinator at Oceanaire Seafood Room. There Lee was trained by chef Rob Klink on both managerial and culinary side of food business. Lee and his mother Yesoon Lee opened Mandu in two locations in Washington, D.C., Dupont Circle and later Mount Vernon Triangle. In 2017, Lee, along with Fried Rice Collective members Scott Drewno and Andrew Kim, opened CHIKO in Capitol Hill, Washington, D.C.
      Danny Lee discusses growing up the child of immigrants with influences of Korean culture, food, and language, attending Thomas Jefferson High School for Science and Technology in Alexandria, Virginia, the impact of his father's early death on the family, his mother's restaurant enterprises, attending the University of Virginia in Charlottesville, Virginia, his culinary training, opening Mandu in Dupont Circle and Mount Vernon Triangle, Washington, D.C. with his mother, collaborating with other Washington, D.C. area chefs to form the Fried Rice Collective, opening CHIKO in Capitol Hill, Washington, D.C., his emphasis on providing a healthy work environment, and the impact Korean and Chinese fine dining has made in his life.
    - Edward Lee interview, 2018-07-10; dcpl_dcohc007_05.wav
      Edward Lee was born in Seoul, South Korea and raised in the Canarsie neighborhood in Brooklyn, New York, New York. During his childhood Lee spent time with his grandmother watching her cook, peaking his interest in the culinary arts. He entered the foodservice industry as a busboy at 14 and later worked in the kitchen of the restaurant. He opened Clay, a Korean restaurant, near Chinatown in Manhattan, New York in the 1990s. After the 9/11 terrorist attack Lee moved to Louisville, Kentucky where he opened the restaurants 610 Magnolia, MilkWood, and Whiskey Dry. Lee is the author of a cookbook Smoke & Pickles and a food memoir titled Buttermilk Graffiti. He has made numerous appearances on television shows, including Top Chef, The Mind of a Chef, and Culinary Genius. He opened a southern cuisine restaurant, Succotash, in National Harbor, Maryland and later Penn Quarter, Washington, D.C.
      Edward Lee discusses his childhood in the Canarsie neighborhood in Brooklyn, New York, New York, his desire from a young age to be in the kitchen, entering the foodservice industry at the age of 14 as a busboy, his short stint at Peter Kump's New York Cooking School, opening his first restaurant Clay, the enormous strain of his early success, moving to Louisville, Kentucky to reset personally and professionally, opening Succotash in National Harbor, Maryland then Washington, D.C., his views on foodie culture, his work in mentoring women in the food industry through The LEE Initiate, the differences between life in Louisville, Kentucky and Washington, D.C., Korean culture and patriarchy, and his views on gentrification.
    - Seng Luangrath interview part 1, 2018-09-25; dcpl_dcohc007_02_1.wav
      Seng Luangrath was born in Vientiane, Laos where she grew up in a multi-generational home and learned to cook from her grandmother. At the age of 12, Luangrath fled Laos with her mother and brothers; her sister, who was viewed to be braver than Luangrath, stayed behind to care for her grandmother. Her family lived in refugee camps in Thailand and the Philippines. While living in a refugee camp in Nakhon Phanom, Thailand, her mother remarried and Luangrath learned to cook various Lao regional cuisines from her stepfather. In the Philippines her family attended an English language school in preparation for moving to Berkeley, California in the United States. Luangrath attended Berkeley High School and then Laney College. In 1988 Luangrath married a man through a courtship her mother arranged, and moved with her new husband to Northern Virginia. Luangrath worked as a bank teller and accountant while her husband worked in manufacturing, food service, and flooring before the pair started a construction business for military housing. The business ultimately failed leaving the couple looking for new options. Luangrath dreamed of opening her own restaurant and the opportunity arose to take over a Thai restaurant, Bangkok Golden (now Padaek) in Falls Church, Virginia. The original menu featured Thai food but included secret Lao dishes. After a positive review from a Washington Post food critic, Luangrath began serving both Thai and Lao dishes. With encouragement from her customers and the Washington, D.C. chef community, she opened Thip Khao in Columbia Heights, Washington, D.C. with her son, Bobby Pradachith. Together Luangrath and Pradachith lead the Lao Food Movement which promotes Lao cuisine and culture and encourages ethnic minorities to be proud of their identities and cultures.
      Seng Luangrath discusses her childhood in Vientiane, Laos, living in a multi-generational home, learning to cook from her grandmother, the impact of the Laotian Civil War and the Vietnam War on her family, attending a French-language school, learning that her family would be escaping Laos but that her sister would remain with her grandmother, the experience of being smuggled across the Laos border into Thailand, life as a refugee in Thailand then the Philippines, attending an English language school in preparation for moving to Berkeley, California, her marriage arranged by her mother, moving to Virginia and establishing a life with her new husband, her professional life before becoming a chef, opening her first restaurant and then expanding into Washington, D.C., her lifelong passion for cooking and serving her community, and the impact the community of chefs in Washington, D.C. have had on her career.
    - Seng Luangrath interview part 2, 2018-09-25; dcpl_dcohc007_02_2.wav
    - Yesoon Lee interview, 2019-08-20; dcpl_dcohc007_03.wav
      Yesoon Lee was born in Seoul, Korea in 1946. She attended South Gate Elementary School, Sudo Girl's High School, and Lee University. Lee attended graduate school for music composition at the University of Illinois at Champaign-Urbana where she met and married her husband. Lee and her husband moved to Northern Virginia where she taught at Averett College in Danville, Virginia and operated Pica-deli in Alexandria, Virginia with a friend. Lee's husband passed away from cancer, leaving her looking for new ways to support her family. She operated a Charlie Chiang's Kwai in Ronald Reagan National Airport and later opened Mandu in Dupont Circle and Mount Vernon Square, Washington, D.C. with her son, Danny Lee. Yeeson is a member of McLean Bible Church.
      Yesoon Lee discusses her childhood in Seoul, Korea during and after the Korean War, attending graduate school for music composition at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign where she met and married her husband, moving to Northern Virginia, teaching at Averett College in Danville, Virginia, operating Pica-deli in Alexandria, Virginia, the impact the early death of her husband had on her life, opening Charlie Chiang's Kwai in Ronald Reagan National Airport, opening Mandu in Dupont Circle and Mount Vernon Triangle, Washington, D.C. with her son Danny Lee, her religious beliefs, her perspective on the chef community in Washington, D.C., and her family.
  - Sub-Series 2: Indexes and Transcripts
    - Bobby Pradachith interview index, 2018-05-29; dcpl_dcohc007_01_ind.pdf
    - Bobby Pradachith interview transcript, 2018-05-29; dcpl_dcohc007_01_tra.pdf
    - Danny Lee interview index, 2018-08-21; dcpl_dcohc007_02_ind.pdf
    - Danny Lee interview transcript, 2018-08-22; dcpl_dcohc007_02_tra.pdf
    - Danny Lee interview Mandu menu, 2018-08-22; dcpl_dcohc007_02_menu_mandu.pdf
    - Edward Lee interview index, 2018-07-11; dcpl_dcohc007_03_ind.pdf
    - Edward Lee interview transcript, 2018-07-12; dcpl_dcohc007_03_tra.pdf
    - Edward Lee interview Succotash menu, 2018-07-12; dcpl_dcohc007_03_menu_succotash.pdf
    - Seng Luangrath interview index, 2018-09-25; dcpl_dcohc007_04_ind.pdf
    - Seng Luangrath interview transcript, 2018-09-25; dcpl_dcohc007_04_tra.pdf
    - Seng Luangrath Thip Khao menu, 2018-09-25; dcpl_dcohc007_04_menu_thipkhao.pdf
    - Yesoon Lee interview index, 2019-08-20; dcpl_dcohc007_05_ind.pdf
    - Yesoon Lee interview transcript, 2019-08-20; dcpl_dcohc007_05_tra.pdf
- Series 9: D.C. Jazz Festival Oral History Project, 2017
  This project captures the history and topical insights of community members who have contributed to jazz in Washington, D.C. The project interviewed musicians, historians, educators, media, and presenters.
  The D.C. Jazz Festival Oral History Project contains four audio interviews conducted by Rusty Hassan and Willard Jenkins in 2017. Indexes and transcripts are included for all interviews.
  Festivals; Music
  - Sub-Series 1: Interviews, 2017
    - Brother Ah interview part 1, 2017-08-21
      Robert 'Bob' Northern, known professionally as Brother Ah, is an American jazz French hornist. Born in North Carolina and raised in The Bronx, Northern studied at the Manhattan School of Music and at the Vienna State Academy in the 1950s. He is perhaps best known as a session musician, working extensively in the 1950s and 1960s with musicians such as Donald Byrd, John Coltrane, Gil Evans, Sun Ra, McCoy Tyner, Roland Kirk, and the Jazz Composers Orchestra. He also worked with Don Cherry, Thelonious Monk, Freddie Hubbard, Miles Davis, Dizzy Gillespie, Eric Dolphy, Charlie Haden, and John Lewis.
      He lived in New York City from 1963 to 1971, and after a period of increasing interest in non-Western music, visited and studied in Africa (Ghana, Kenya and Tanzania) during seven consecutive summers (1972 -1977). In the 1970s he released several albums as a bandleader; his 1974 release Sound Awareness featured Max Roach and M'Boom. These albums were reissued on CD on the Ikef Records label in the 2000s. In addition to horn playing, Northern also branched into percussion and flute performance later in his career. He taught at Dartmouth College from 1970 to 1973, Brown University from 1973 to 1982 and then at the Levine School of Music in Washington, D.C. from 1982. Northern is also the founder of the World Music Ensemble, a group which explores African, Japanese, Spanish, East Indian, Native American and American musical traditions and the founder of The Sounds of Awareness Ensemble which explores the sounds of nature and music. Northern, as Brother Ah, hosts a weekly jazz oriented radio program, The Jazz Collectors, on station WPFW in Washington.
      In this oral history Broth Ah speaks about his life in, and love for, Jazz music. He speaks about his family migrating north after his father had a confrontation with the Klu Klux Klan. As a young child growing up in Harlem and the Bronx in New York City, he learned the Bugle. He then enrolled in a prestigious performing arts school in New York, there he felt pressure from being one of just six black students. Military service in Korea interrupted his college education. In New York, he played in the most prestigious venues in the world, including Carnegie Hall, where he experienced racial discrimination, and legendary Jazz Clubs such as Birdland where he got to know Miles Davis and John Coltrane. He then moves to be a music professor at Dartmouth and Brown. The remainder of the oral history is dedicated to Brother Ah's time in Washington D.C. He speaks about encountering Washington, D.C. as "Chocolate City," and the thrill of playing at the Lincoln Theatre and Howard Theatre. The reader is informed that D.C. had the best ribs in America. He speaks about a lecture series on Jazz that he gave at the Smithsonian and, later, University of the District of Columbia. A wonderful story about how firefighters helped him to save his instruments. In recent years, Brother Ah has run a popular Jazz focused radio show on WPFW.
    - Brother Ah interview part 2, 2017-08-21
    - Brother Ah interview part 3, 2017-08-21
    - Charles Fishman interview part 1, 2017-09-01
      Charles Fishman, born in Brooklyn, New York, February 13, 1942, is Founder of the D.C. Jazz Festival. A Grammy Award-winning producer, he is also the founder and president of Charismatic Productions, a Washington, D.C.-based production, and consulting established in 1986. Recognized internationally among the foremost producers of Jazz concerts, festivals, and tours, Fishman has produced projects at such prestigious venues as Carnegie Hall, the Hollywood Bowl, the Dorothy Chandler Pavilion, the Kennedy Center, Lincoln Theatre, The National Mall, Place des Artes, Filene Center at Wolf Trap National Park for the Performing Arts, other notable venues. He was the personal manager and producer of jazz legend Dizzy Gillespie until the Maestro's death. He has produced nine audio recordings and five television programs that have been aired on PBS, ABC, Bravo, the BBC and other international networks. Washingtonian Magazine (October 2008) listed Fishman as "one of the 50 men and women who have transformed Washington into one of the nation's liveliest centers for the performing arts."
      In this oral history, Charles Fishman discusses how he developed a love for Jazz music. Though his parents did not allow him to study music in college, it is not long before he makes Jazz into his life's work. An early milestone in his career was opening an Jazz club in Israel. He speaks about how he worked with Jazz legends, including producing a world tour with Dizzy Gillespie. Finally, he speaks about moving to D.C. and continuing to spread Jazz in the nation's capital.
    - Charles Fishman interview part 2, 2017-09-01
      Charles Fishman, born in Brooklyn, New York, February 13, 1942, is Founder of the D.C. Jazz Festival. A Grammy Award-winning producer, he is also the founder and president of Charismatic Productions, a Washington, D.C.-based production, and consulting established in 1986. Recognized internationally among the foremost producers of Jazz concerts, festivals, and tours, Fishman has produced projects at such prestigious venues as Carnegie Hall, the Hollywood Bowl, the Dorothy Chandler Pavilion, the Kennedy Center, Lincoln Theatre, The National Mall, Place des Arts, Filene Center at Wolf Trap National Park for the Performing Arts, other notable venues. He was the personal manager and producer of jazz legend Dizzy Gillespie until the Maestro's death. He has produced nine audio recordings and five television programs that have been aired on PBS, ABC, Bravo, the BBC and other international networks. Washingtonian Magazine (October 2008) listed Fishman as "one of the 50 men and women who have transformed Washington into one of the nation's liveliest centers for the performing arts."
    - Judith Korey interview part 1, 2017-09-08
      Judith A. Korey, born and raised in Philadelphia, PA on October 8, 1947, is Professor of Music at the University of the District of Columbia, joined the faculty of the University's predecessor institution, Federal City College in 1972. She currently serves as the Music Program Coordinator in the Division of Arts and Humanities, College of Arts and Sciences and previously acted as chairperson for the Department of Visual and Performing Arts. She is a graduate of Chestnut Hill College in Philadelphia, and the Catholic University of America, Washington, D.C. where she received a Master of Arts degree in Musicology with a Major in Music Theory.
      In addition to her administrative and teaching assignments, Professor Korey is curator of the University's acclaimed jazz research and resource center, the Felix E. Grant Jazz Archives. She has represented the Archives on panels and presentations at conferences, forums and festivals. In 2016, the Felix E. Grant Jazz Archives was chosen by the Howard University Jazz Ensemble to receive the prestigious "Benny Golson Jazz Master Award."
      Professor Korey also coordinates the Music Program and JAZZAlive events calendars. Produced by the Jazz Studies program and the Felix E. Grant Jazz Archives, the JAZZAlive events series presents a diversity of jazz related events year-round culminating with the Calvin Jones BIG BAND Jazz Festival, an annual event that has been overwhelmingly supported by area audiences since 1987. She has worked collaboratively with UDC-TV to produce programming from the JAZZAlive events that are broadcast regularly on the station.
      In 2008 Prof. Korey was awarded the University of the District of Columbia's Dr. Cleveland Dennard Service Award, which is presented to an individual who has demonstrated a long-term commitment of outstanding service to the University. In 2015 she received the Accomplishment in Leadership Award from the College of Arts and Sciences, and in 2016 the University presented her with the Pathmaker Leadership Award. Professor Korey was also honored with the 24th Annual Mayor's Arts Award for Excellence in Service to the Arts-2009, and the Jazz Journalist Associations Jazz Hero Award in 2017.
      Judith Korey, she speaks about growing up in a musical family and building an interest in Jazz through a teenage love of the Blues. Seeing Buddy Guy play at her college was a milestone in the development of her musical interests. She went on to study for a doctorate at Catholic University, during which time she started teaching music theory at the University of the District of Columbia (UDC). At UDC she would eventually design the music program. She talks about was launching a Big Band Festival in 1987 that has run for 32 years and counting, and about starting WD.C.U, the University of the District of Columbia's radio station. Throughout the oral history the reader gets a strong sense of Judith's passion for sharing jazz with the D.C. community and beyond.
    - Judith Korey interview part 2, 2017-09-08
    - Judith Korey interview part 3, 2017-09-08
    - Judith Korey interview part 4, 2017-09-08
    - Rusty Hassan interview, 2017-07-21
      Rusty Hassan, born in Bound Brook, NJ November 26, 1945, and raised in Greenwich, CT, has been the producer and host for weekly jazz radio programs for the past fifty years, starting as a student at Georgetown University on WGTB. Since then he has hosted shows on WAMU, WD.C.U and WPFW. He currently hosts Thursday Night Jazz on WPFW 89.3FM. Among the prominent jazz artists he has interviewed include Dexter Gordon, Art Blakey, Mary Lou Williams, Ramsey Lewis, Jimmy Heath, and numerous others.
      He was a union representative with the American Federation of Government Employees for thirty-four years. He has taught jazz history courses at American University, Georgetown University, University of Maryland University College and the Smithsonian Institution. He currently teaches at the University of the District of Columbia. The D.C. Commission on the Arts and Humanities recognized him with a special award for his contribution to the community with his years of broadcasting in Washington, D.C.
      Rusty Hassan talks about falling in love with Jazz music as a teenager, especially the music of John Coltrane and how the music gave him an education about race in America. He then speaks about moving to Washington, D.C. to attend Georgetown University where he continues his interest in Jazz, eventually getting involved in labor and community organizing while attending D.C.'s legendary jazz clubs including Blues Alley and the Cellar Door. He continues to stay involved in the jazz world by DJing for WAMU and WPFW, while he develops his career in labor. Finally, he speaks about how he continues to cultivate more enthusiasm for jazz through teaching courses on jazz at universities around D.C.
  - Sub-Series 2: Indexes, 2017
    - Brother Ah index, 2017
    - Charles Fishman index, 2017
    - Judith Korey index, 2017
    - Rusty Hassan index, 2017
  - Sub-Series 3: transcripts, 2017
    - Brother Ah transcript, 2017
    - Charles Fishman transcript, 2017
    - Judith Korey transcript, 2017
    - Rusty Hassan transcript, 2017
- Series 10: Oral History of DanceAfrica, D.C., 2018
  DanceAfrica is a celebration of dance forms of the African Diaspora and is held annually in Washington, D.C., New York, New York, and Chicago, Illinois. The festival includes performance, films, master classes, educational programming, and a bazaar. This oral history project features six interviews with members of the DanceAfrica, D.C. elders' council.
  The Oral History of DanceAfrica, D.C. contains six audio interviews conducted by Sarah Greenbaum and Jonathan Hsu in 2018. Indexes and transcripts are included for all interviews.
  Dance; Festivals
  - Sub-Series 1: Interviews, 2018
    - Sylvia Soumah interview, 2018-05-18
      Sylvia Soumah is the founder and Artistic Director of Coyaba Dance Theater. She has studied, performed, and taught throughout the D.C. Metro area and abroad. She has studied in Conakry, Guinea with Les Ballets Africains, and Senegal under the director of Bouly Sonko, Artistic Director of the National Ballet of Senegal. She also performs with Erika Thimey Dance Theater and Carla & Company. Born and raised in Cincinnati, Ohio, she moved to Washington, D.C. in 1985.